Guide to the Medical Center records, 1825-2005 RG0007
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- GW Medicine and Health magazine, 1965-2016; RG0007 Series 27; 2.5 Linear feet (Box 1, Box 2, Box 3, Box 4, Box 5)
  - GW Medicine and Health Magazine: Fall, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - GW Medicine and Health Magazine: Spring, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - GW Medicine and Health Magazine: Spring, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - GW Medicine and Health Magazine: Spring, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - GW Medicine and Health Magazine: Fall, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - GW Medicine and Health Magazine: Summer, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - GW Medicine and Health Magazine: Winter, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - GW Medicine and Health Magazine: Summer, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - GW Medicine and Health Magazine: Winter, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - GW Medicine and Health Magazine: Summer, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - GW Medicine and Health Magazine: Winter, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - GW Medicine and Health Magazine: Summer/Fall, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - GW Medicine and Health Magazine: Winter, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - GW Medicine and Health Magazine: Summer, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - GW Medicine and Health Magazine: Winter, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - GW Medicine and Health Magazine: Summer, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - GW Medicine and Health Magazine: Winter, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - GW Medicine and Health Magazine: Fall/Winter, 2008 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - GW Medicine and Health Magazine: Summer 2009 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - GW Medicine and Health Magazine, Spring 2010 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - GW Medicine and Health Magazine, Winter 2011 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - GW Medicine and Health Magazine: Summer 2006 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - GW Medicine and Health Magazine: Spring 2007 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - GW Medicine and Health Magazine: Fall 2011 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - GW Medicine and Health Magazine: Fall 2013 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - GW Medicine and Health Magazine: Spring 2013, Series 27 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - GW Medicine and Health Magazine: Spring 2014, Series 27 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - GW Medicine and Health Magazine: Fall 2014, Series 27 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - GW Medicine and Health Magazine: Spring 2015, Series 27 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - GW Medicine and Health Magazine: Fall 2015, Series 27 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - GW Medicine and Health Magazine: Fall 2016, Series 27 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - GW Medicine and Health Magazine: Spring 2017 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Photographs, 1923-1926; RG0007 Series 28; 0.25 Linear feet (Box 1)
  This series consists of five photos of Nursing School graduates and staff, and range in date from 1923-26.
  - George Washington Hospital Graduates, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Nursing School
  - George Washington Hospital Graduating Class, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - George Washington Hospital Graduating Class -- Staff -- Personnel, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - George Washington Hospital Graduates, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - George Washington Hospital Graduates, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- State Health Notes newsletter, 1979-1990; RG0007 Series 29; 0.5 Linear feet (Box 1)
  This series consists of "State Health Notes," the intergovernmental health policy project newsletter on health care issues. The materials range in date from 1979-90.
- GW Progress, 1989-2009; RG0007 Series 30; 1 Linear foot (Box 1, Box 2)
  This series consists of "Progress," a newsletter for faculty, staff, and students of the GW Medical Center. The material ranges in date from 1989-2009.
  - GW Progress, March-October 2007 (Box SHARED Box 3, Folder 3)
- Records, 1825-2004; RG0007 Series 32; 3 Linear feet (Box 1, Box 2, Box 3, Box 4)
  This series includes correspondence, brochures, floor plans, memorandums, executive summaries, reports, publications, programs, articles, press releases, calendar of events, schedules, reports, vitas, applications, agendas, meeting minutes, speeches, course catalogues, window stickers, forms, posters, and applications. They range in date from 1825 to 2004. The materials concern the Medical Center, lectures, services, patient education, the Allergy Clinic, audiovisual services, diets, budgets, the Center for Health Policy Research, the Center to Improve Care of the Dying, the Health Policy committee, conferences, computer applications, dedication of Ross Hall, symposiums, several departmental publications, films, various public health information brochures, medical research, residency programs, financial planning, University Hospital, internships, fellowships, research, committees, ethics, the Medical Association of the District of Columbia, history of the School of Medicine, planning, opening assemblies, closing assemblies, seminars, the School of Medicine and Health Sciences, "GWU Prognosis", admissions, financial assistance, the School of Public Health and Health Services, the National Health Policy Forum, seminars, and the Department of Public Health program. Some people mentioned include Dr. Frank Nelson Miller, Jr., Dr. Seymour Alpert, John Parks, and Angus M. Griffin. Some brochures are in Spanish.
  - Alumni - Medical, 1972-1998 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alumni - Medical Reunions Class of 1927, 02/24/1967 -10/14/1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Alumni - Medical Reunions, 1920-1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Alumni - Medical Reunions, 1991-1995 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Alumni - Medical Reunions, 1996-1998 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Alumni - Medical Reunions, 1999-2003 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Convocations/Commencements - Commencement - Invitations National Medical College/Medical School, 1884-1903 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Convocations/Commencements - Commencement - Medicine and Health Sciences, School of, 1959-1998 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Convocations/Commencements - Commencement Nurses, School of, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Convocations/Commencements - Commencement Tickets - National Medical College, 1874 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Dental School--History, 1906-1965 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Medical Center, 1971 -05/11/2004 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Medical Center--Allergy Clinic--Patient Education Materials, 09/01/1967 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Medical Center--Audiovisual Services, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Medical Center Budget Manual, 1993-1994, 01/15/1993 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Medical Center - Center For Health Policy Research, 1994-04/1997 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Medical Center - Center to Improve the Care of the Dying, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Medical Center - Committee on Health Policy - Publications, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Medical Center--Conferences, Workshops, Symposia, 02/1961-1997 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Medical Center--Continuing Medical Education, Office of, 09/13/1979 -06/19/1982 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Medical Center - Dedication of Ross Hall, May 24, 1973, 05/24/1975 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Medical Center - Department of Biochemistry, 09/28/1979 -05/18/1990 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Medical Center-- Department of Dermatology, 11/22/1977 -10/17/1982 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Medical Center-- Department of Gastroenterology, 06/11/1988 -06/18/1988 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Medical Center-- Department of Health Services Management and Policy -Administrative Residency Manual, 07/1996 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Medical Center-- Department of Medical and Public Affairs, 12/21/1965 -02/07/1978 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Medical Center-- Department of Medical and Public Affairs--Population Field Information Services, 1974-01/1979 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Medical Center-- Department of Obstetrics & GYN.--Publications, 10/29/1985 -11/10/1978 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Medical Center-- Department of Physiology, 1965 -06/05/2004 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Medical Center - Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences - Residency Training Program, 1981, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Medical Center-- Department of Surgery--Post-Graduate & Specialty Programs, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Medical Center -- Development and Alumni Relations -- Estate and Gift Planning, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Medical Center--Division of Hematology, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Medical Center - Faculty, 04/12/1952 -04/02/1996 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes information about professor of pathology, Frank N. Miller, M.D., as well as unpublished articles by Dr. Miller such as "The Fever and the Fret."
  - Medical Center - History, 1973 -04/19/1991 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Medical Center--Internship, Residency & Fellowship Programs, 09/1965-1970 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Medical Center - Publications, 08/1972-06/2000 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Medical Center - Research, 02/1961 -02/14/1979 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Medical Center University Clinic, 10/27/1968 -03/20/1969 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Medical School--Admissions, 1966-11/1971 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Medical School--Career Electives, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Medical School--Conferences, Workshops, Symposium, Seminars, 03/03/1954 -1978 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Medical School -- Deans [1/2], 1956-1972 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Medical School -- Deans [2/2], 1956-1957 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Medical School--Early Faculty--Participation In Medical Society of D.C., 1827-1869 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Medical School--Faculty--Representation In Membership Of Medical Association Of The District of Columbia, 1873-1899 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Medical School--History, 1943-04/1998 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Medical School - History, 1825-1900, 02/13/1826 -11/15/1978 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Medical School - History, 1901-2001, 1896 -05/21/2001 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Medical School--History--Medical Dept. (N.E. Corner 10th & E Streets, N.W. 1826-1834; 1839- 1844), 08/1825 -04/01/1970 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Medical School --- History--National Medical College - Consolidation With Columbian Medical School, 1903 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Medical School--History--National Medical College (Medical Department of Columbian College)-- History --Transcripts of Articles Appearing in The Capital, 1871-75 (Work of Professor Ragatz), 10/02/1871 -09/12/1875 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Medical School--History--Washington Infirmary, 1844-1861, 10/24/1972 -11/06/1972 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Medical School--History--World War II Period, 11/1943 -11/1946 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Medical School--Microbiology Department, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Medical School-- Opening and closing assemblies, 10/01/1892 -09/10/1971 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Medical School--Planning And Development, 02/1965 -01/22/1970 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Medical School--Postgraduate Courses and Seminars, 04/18/1938 -03/26/1956 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Medical School - Postgraduate Courses and Seminars Proceedings Psychiatry and Neurology, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Medical School - Research, 10/1925 -04/1967 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Medical School - Schedules of classes, 1938-1972 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Medical School--Students, 1852-1974 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Medical School--Students - Follies, 1975 -04/03/1993 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Medical School--Tuition, 10/19/1972 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Medical School Yearbooks, 09/1944 -08/25/1979 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Medicine And Health Sciences, School of, 01/21/1974 -07/01/1997 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Medicine And Health Sciences, School of (1973- ) - Admissions, 1979-2001 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Medicine And Health Sciences, School of, (1973- )--Brochures, 2000-2004 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Medicine And Health Sciences, School of, (1973- )--Conferences, Workshops, Symposia, Seminars, 04/21/1979 -03/14/1981 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Medicine And Health Sciences, School of (1973- )--Financial Aid Office, undated (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Medicine And Health Sciences, School of--Physician's Assistant Program, 1972-1978 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Medicine And Health Sciences, School of - Student Handbook, 1996, 08/21/1996 -08/23/1996 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - National Health Policy Forum, 1978-1980, 06/28/1978 -10/30/1980 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - National Health Policy Forum, 1981-1982, 01/22/1981 -12/09/1982 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - National Health Policy Forum, 1983-1986, 01/12/1983 -05/19/1986 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Public Health, Department of (1904-2002), 02/20/1904 -03/29/2002 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Public Health and Health Services, School of, 1997-1999 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Hospital Promotional Materials, 1996-2006 (Box SHARED Box 3, Folder 4)
- GW Health Plan, 1968-1972; RG0007 Series 33; 0.50 Linear Feet (Box 1)
  Documents related to the establishment of a health plan at GW. The documents include: The original proposal, together with Dr. Elliott's letter; The founding and related documents from the three pioneering medical schools: 1) the Harvard Community Health Plan, designed in cooperation with Blue Cross / Blue Shield to serve the metropolitan Boston community. (Exists today as the highly successful Harvard Pilgrim Health Care. 2) the Yale Health Plan, designed to serve the faculty and staff of Yale University. 3) the Johns Hopkins program, designed to serve the planned community in Columbia, Maryland; Federal legislation and regulations involving the development of HMOs; Necessary service agreements with organizations to include Blue Cross /Blue Shield committed to providing recruitment into the health plan, and reinsurance against catastrophic loss to complex patients; and the District of Columbia commitment to prepay patients enrolled from the Medicaid-eligible population of the district; Planning documents necessary to implement the health plan, and create the necessary separate corporation (entirely controlled by the University) to administer it; Legal considerations and documents provided by Fred Vinson (of Reasoner, Davis, and Vinson), University attorney at the time.
  Biographical / Historical
  The George Washington University Health Plan was proposed by the Division of General Medicine in the Department of Medicine in 1971. Dr. Thomas Piemme was the Director of the Division. Piemme had made his intentions known to the Chair of Medicine, Wallace Jensen, to the Dean, John Parks, and to the Associate Dean for Clinical Affairs, James Feffer before he arrived at the University on January 1, 1970 and had their approval. Moreover, he had a "Special Project Grant" from the Bureau of Health Manpower in which development of an HMO was a part.
  During the summer of 1971. Jim Feffer and Dr. Piemme attended a conference in Los Angeles, conducted by the Kaiser Health Plan, to learn the fundamentals of organizing pre-paid health plans. Piemme was joined in the Division in early 1971 by Steven A. Schroeder, whom he had recruited from Harvard.
  Together, Steve and Dr. Piemme then visited Harvard, Yale, and Johns Hopkins the three medical schools that, at the time, had developed university-based HMOs. During the course of their travels and other research, they accumulated the documents necessary to an understanding of what they were about to recommend. The men then wrote a proposal that was submitted to Lloyd Elliott, President of the University.
  In early 1972 Dr. Elliott wrote to Dr. Piemme approving the plan to proceed.
  Conditions Governing Access
  The series is open for research.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Materials donated in 2021 by Dr. Thomas Piemme.
  - Proposal and Elliott approval, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Other medical school examples - Harvard, Yale, Hopkins, 1968-1972 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - Federal legislation, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Source documents, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - General planning documents, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)